Hello and welcome back to
another video with it's Dr. Dan.
And today we're gonna be going through
the tips and tricks on isomers,
specifically constitutional isomers,
which is when we have different branching
patterns on the different alkane.
Alkane are typically the
different hydrocarbons.
So these ones that we're gonna
specifically doing today is octane, which
you might kind of realize is the more
carbons you add, the more isomers you get.
So we're gonna show how to find all
18 isomers, and I'm gonna go through
the exact steps on how to do this so
that way if you're given a different
structure like hexane or heptane or non,
or whatever, you know how to find all
the different isomers that are possible.
So now why is this something
that's important is all because of
intermolecular forces when we have all
these different, uh, types of chemicals.
So they give these things different
properties, which is the whole reason
why we even care about these isomers.
Every single one of them
is a little bit unique.
They might all have the exact
same chemical formula, but they
all have different structures.
Therefore, they're gonna have
slightly different properties
that are gonna be behind them.
So you're gonna see like their
melting points and boiling
points and things like that.
They're gonna, they're
gonna adjust slightly.
With the different branching
patterns they have because they can
interact differently with each other.
All right, so when you're doing
your different isomers, first
step is we always wanna start
with what the longest chain is.
This is, you're never, this is
gonna be your only straight chain
ice m. Everything else is gonna be
completely gonna be, uh, have branches.
So when you're kind of doing
this, you can do it in two ways.
So let's say if we were look through
expanded structures, which is usually
where most organic students start, I
usually, if I'm, let's say if I had to
do it this way, I usually will write
down like all my carbons first, right?
And then I just wanna like
kind of number them, right?
We can kind of see one, two.
4, 5, 6, 7, 8. So I'm always kind of
keeping a mental count for myself.
Now as we're gonna be moving on, we're
gonna be kind of taking off like this last
carbon here, and we're gonna be moving
into different locations on this chain.
Now when it comes to ice Rs
though, the easiest way though
is doing line structure.
You can do expanded.
We can fill in all the hydrogens, but you
realize it's gonna take a lot of time.
So what I usually do is I'll just
kind of draw the lines, right?
So I got 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6,
7, and then eight, right?
So that's gonna be my base chain.
And then from there, what we're gonna use
that as is like a template for ourselves.
So this one is our
first one out of the 18.
So let's go to step two and
see what we can do with that.
So for step two, we're gonna be
removing one carbon at a time, and
we're gonna be creating a methyl branch.
So keep in mind the most important
thing for when you're doing these
is keep count of your carbons.
When you're going through this, you
need to have eight the entire time.
So it's really easy to do this and
add an extra carbon here or there.
So I'm gonna copy and paste
my octane from before.
I'm going to delete one of
these carbons at the end.
So right now I have a total of seven
carbons that we can see in our chain.
So we have, heptane is our longest,
and what we're gonna be doing is making
a branch at the different positions.
So, for example, if I do this right, I
can put a branch, let's say at carbon
number two as one of my choices.
Now, is that the only option
that you could have as an isomer?
Well, let's just move it
to different locations.
We could move, uh, a branch at carbon
Number three, we could also put a methyl
branch also at carbon number four as well.
All these are different
possibilities that you have.
Now when you're going through this, you
want to make sure that you are, you're
naming right, so we have like two methyl
heptane, three methyl heptane, and then
the last one is four methyl heptane.
Now you want to keep checking
your numbering to make sure
you're not doing any duplicates.
That can happen because essentially
we kind of think of like the four
methyl heptane as our last one.
If I were to keep going
and I put a branch at five.
That would've made a
duplicate of number three.
So it's really easy to make doubles.
So on here, right?
Right now, how many do we have?
We now have four of the
total 18 that are here.
So let's keep going and we're gonna
remove another carbon and continue.
So as I was saying, you want to make
sure you write down your names as you go.
You don't want to have any type
of duplicates or confirmers.
As you're going through all
these different structures.
So con confirmers is just a fancy way of
saying, Hey, this structure's rotating.
So it's very easy to kind of do that.
What I mean is a lot of students,
they'll draw their structure.
So let's say if I had, uh, seven
carbons, so a hept-, so a heptane, right?
So I got 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, and seven.
You can never add a branch onto
carbon number one or the last carbon.
So like I'll commonly see, let's say
someone adds a CH3 branch to the very
beginning or something, but alls it
does is redefine your longest chain.
So this is like a repeat of octane, right?
'cause it's still that eight carbons long.
So be careful when you're kind of doing
that so that way you don't accidentally
make a duplicate and then you lose
points on an assignment or a test.
Just because you accidentally made
a duplicate, it's super easy to do.
But if you check your names right
and check the longest chain every
time, then you'll realize like,
okay, we, we are, are avoiding any
duplicates that can occur, right?
So let's try to continue with trying to
figure out the rest of these isomers.
So as we're gonna go through, what
we're gonna do is we're gonna keep
repeating step two, which is where
we make a, a new methyl group.
So as you go and you make it shorter,
you're gonna have like two methyl
groups moving around when you
have like just a six member chain.
And if you go lower to five, you'll have
like three methyl groups moving around.
You might be able to try ethyl and
props as a possibility for chains.
You just have to be careful that you
keep naming and looking for the longest
chain because YLS are, be, are possible
with octane, but props will not be.
You need to have at least nine
carbons for that to be a possibility.
Um, when it comes to one of the
isomers, so usually you have to
have a very, very large molecule.
So kind of like a little bit
like of a rule of thumb here.
So like when we did Octane, right,
we had zero methyl groups and we did
Heptane, which was our longest chain.
We had one methyl group and we
have hexane as our, as our, uh.
As our base, we're gonna
have two methyl groups.
And when we get to pentane, we have three.
And it'll keep going until
you, you run outta room, right?
So you gotta keep in mind, you
have to have all of those, uh,
all those different, um, uh, all
the carbons have to be present.
So if I were to redraw this hexane, right?
So now the whole idea is, all
right, what are all the different
possibilities for drawing these isomers?
So like, for example, I could
put, let's say a methyl on.
Two and four.
Right?
And that's a possibility
that we could have here.
So we could have two four dimethyl taxane
and we could keep going with that, right?
So we could put them, let's say
on two and three as an option.
So we could do two, three dimethyl taxane.
What we're gonna keep doing is
we're gonna keep repeating all
the different possibilities here.
So we could have, what else?
We could have two, two dimethyl heine.
So we're just gonna try to go through
all of these possibilities, right, uh,
as we're kind of going through them.
So just to kind of like
fast forward for you guys.
So you have to watch me like figure
out like all the possibilities.
Let's go through all the ones that
are possible for having two branches.
And if you want to pause here
to see, can you figure it out?
That's a good time to do that.
So let's see if you get all the same
number that are for two methyl groups
moving around a few moments later.
Okay, so to fast forward, I started
to write out all the names for this.
So we had the first two, right,
which were two, four and two three.
So from there you, you're essentially
come up with every possible number
combination you can think of.
So I can get up to 10
of the isomers this way.
So my next one would be three, four.
So we'll put a branch on the
third carbon on the fourth.
Then we have another one where
we have it on two and five.
You can double them up.
So let's say if I put two of
them on the same position.
Right.
So they're like two little bunny ears
kind of sitting on, on the structure,
right, on one of these carbons.
And then you could go to the next one,
which would be three, three, um, and you
can kind of see like, okay, you can't
go to four four, because then you're
gonna make a duplicate of this structure.
So that's where it's gonna
end for this particular one.
Now, is there any other type
of carbon that is possible?
Um, you could potentially do,
uh, you could do hels as well.
So how many hel possibilities are
there where you gotta kind of play
with like the different positions?
Because you gotta make sure you're
not redefining the longest chain.
So typically it has to be like
at leased on carbon number three
in order for an Ethel group.
To be possible, right?
So if we kind of see on the very
bottom here, I have it on, on
the bottom, and it's not gonna
redefine what your longest chain is.
So like we could have three ethyl, uh,
hexane as one of our possibilities.
And propyl wouldn't be possible when
you get the five because it's gonna
make your longest chain something else.
So these are all the different
possibilities that we could
have for just two branches.
So what we're now we're gonna
do is we're gonna move to five.
So let's try to do pentane and
we're gonna try to come up with
the next, uh, I think like six
more that are possible for pentane.
The first one, right, we have,
I drew a bunch of pentanes, so
we're gonna try to figure out all
the possible combinations here.
So now we're gonna do three methyl
groups moving to different locations.
So like, let's say if I pick that
first one here, so let's say if I
just put a methyl group on, we'll
do two, three, and four, right?
So if we were to do this one,
we could see, okay, 2, 3, 4.
And then it would be trimethyl
and being that five carbons as our
longest, it would be pentane, right?
So that'd be one option.
And this is why I kind of like to
line them all up like I'm doing
here on the left hand side of
the, of the page over here, right?
Is 'cause then you can overlap them and
see like all the different combinations
of branching that you can come up with.
Like we could do, let's say we have
two like little bunny ears on carbon
two and then one of them on three.
You could do two little bunny ears on.
Number three, and then one of
them on, on number two, right?
So kind of flipping those two structures
so you could see, okay, we have 2,
2 3, trimethyl pentane, and you're
gonna try to come up with every single
combination that you can think of.
For all these.
Now this is where it kind of
gets tricky 'cause it's a little
easy to do some duplicates.
So we can have like all these different
three options right now from there.
Well, all right, that's all
the methyl possibilities.
But don't forget, we had Ethel earlier,
so what we could do is we could do,
okay, let's do one, one methyl, and
then let's say a ethyl, and then,
all right, well, what's stopping us
from, let's say, doing a methyl and
an ethyl on the same carbon, right?
As another possibility.
Then the one that's missing is that we
have two methyl groups on the first one
and then one methyl on the last one.
I'm like trying to look
through every combination.
It's kind of hard to find them all
sometimes, especially when you have this
many, so, alright, so when it comes to
naming them, right, so we do alphabetical
when it comes to the branches.
So we have three ethyl, two methyl,
uh, pentane, and then we'll have
three ethyl, three methyl pentane.
Then our last one is one more
Trimethyl, which, uh, so be 2, 2 4.
Trimethyl.
Pentane.
Now our last structure, right?
So we have one more possibility
is a, what if we go one shorter.
So what if we do a butane, right?
So we have four carbons that are here.
Can we possibly fit four more?
Four potential methyl
groups on this structure.
And the answer is yes, you can.
We could do where we have, let's say,
two methyl groups on carbon two, and
then let's say two methyl groups on
carbon number, uh, number three, right?
So we have all these little ch
threes on all these structures.
So how the hell do we do that?
Well, we would do 2, 2,
3, 3 tetra, uh, methyl.
Butane would be the structure, and
that's how you can find all of them.
So let's list them all out.
So you have one stop shop for
all the different structures.
Go.
So here is the complete
list of all 18 isomers.
So like if I were to be doing this
on a homework, I would try to do
exactly like what I did on the
left side of this page where I was
attempting to like overlap all these.
So you can kind of see like,
okay, we have, we have eight,
we have seven, we have six.
How long each branch is.
And then we are each parent chain,
and then we start moving our branches
around in different locations
to try to get all 18 of these.
And hopefully you don't have to do this on
a homework, but it's a pretty common one
that I usually see in a lot of homeworks.
I used to give it a lot to my
students, uh, but I kind of
tamed it back a little bit.
Um, but sometimes it's, I've even seen
it on exams where you have to get like
so many of these, uh, on, maybe you
have to get like 12 out of the 18 or
something like that just to show, hey,
you know, how to do isomers or, you
know, some kind of number like that.
So I hope this video helped a little
bit, uh, when it comes to how to draw
the isomers, how to name a little
bit, and just how to go through the
general thought process of how to
approach a problem with this magnitude.
Okay.
Thank you so much for listening,
and I hope you have a wonderful
day and I'll talk to you all later.
Bye now.